Amongst all the troubling deficits we struggle with today --
من ضمن جميع المثبطات المقلقة التي نعاني منها اليوم
we think of financial and economic primarily --
نفكر في المقام الاول في الامور المالية والاقتصادية
the ones that concern me most
واكثر ما يهمني بشكل اكثر
is the deficit of political dialogue --
هو عجز الحوار السياسي--
our ability to address modern conflicts
قدرتنا على فهم الصراعات الحديثة
as they are,
على ماهي عليه,
to go to the source of what they're all about
بالذهاب الى اصلها الفعلي
and to understand the key players
وعلى فهم اللاعبين الرئيسيين
and to deal with them.
وعلى التعامل معهم
We who are diplomats,
نحن الدبلوماسيين
we are trained to deal with conflicts between states and issues between states.
تدربنا على التعامل مع الصراعات بين الدول والقضايا بين الدول.
And I can tell you, our agenda is full.
وبامكاني القول ان جدول اعمالنا ممتلئ
There is trade, there is disarmament,
هناك التجارة,هناك نزع السلاح,
there is cross-border relations.
وهناك علاقات عابرة للحدود
But the picture is changing,
لكن الصورة تتغير
and we are seeing that there are new key players
ونحن نرى ان هناك لاعبين رئيسيين جدد
coming onto the scene.
يظهرون في الصورة.
We loosely call them "groups."
نطلق عليهم مجازا "مجموعات"
They may represent social, religious,
يمكن ان يمثلون مجموعات اجتماعية , دينية,
political, economic, military realities.
سياسية ,اقتصادية ,عسكرية
And we struggle with how to deal with them.
ونحن نتصارع حول كيفية التعامل معهم
The rules of engagement:
قواعد المشاركة والإنخراط :
how to talk, when to talk,
كيف نتحدث , و متى نتحدث,
and how to deal with them.
وكيف نتعامل معاهم.
Let me show you a slide here
دعوني اعرض لكم هذه الشريحة هنا
which illustrates the character of conflicts
والتي توضح صفة هذا الصراعات
since 1946 until today.
منذ 1946 حتى اليوم.
You see the green
ترون الاخضر
is a traditional interstate conflict,
هي صراعات عامة بين الدول,
the ones we used to read about.
النوع الذي اعتدنا القراءة عنه
The red is modern conflict,
الاحمر هو الصراعات الحديثة
conflicts within states.
صراعات داخل الدول
These are quite different,
تلك صراعات مختلفة
and they are outside the grasp
وهي خارج إطار فهم
of modern diplomacy.
للدبلوماسية الحديثة
And the core of these key actors
وجوهر اللاعبين الرئيسيين
are groups
هم المجموعات
who represent different interests
والتي تمثل توجهات مختلفة
inside countries.
داخل الدول
And the way they deal with their conflicts rapidly spreads to other countries.
والطريقة التي يتعاملون بها مع صراعاتهم تنتشر الى الدول الاخرى
So in a way, it is everybody's business.
اذا بعبارة اخرى ، انها مسئولية الجميع
Another acknowledgment we've seen during these years,
وحقيقة اخرى شاهدناها خلال تلك السنين
recent years,
السنين الاخيرة
is that very few
ان القليل من
of these domestic interstate, intrastate conflicts
تلك الصراعات بين الدول وداخل الدول
can be solved militarily.
يمكن حلها عسكريا
They may have to be dealt with with military means,
ربما يتم التعامل معها على اسس عسكرية
but they cannot be solved by military means.
لكن لا يمكن حلها بطرق عسكرية
They need political solutions.
انها تحتاج الى حلول سياسية
And we, therefore, have a problem,
وبالتالي لدينا مشكلة,
because they escape traditional diplomacy.
لأن ذلك يبتعد عن الدبلوماسية التقليدية
And we have among states
ونحن في صدد دول
a reluctance in dealing with them.
يوجد ممانعة في التعامل معها
Plus, during the last decade,
اضافةً لذلك , خلال العقد الماضي
we've been in the mode
كنا في مزاج عام
where dealing with groups
حيث التعامل مع الجماعات
was conceptually and politically dangerous.
كان خطر سياسي ومفهومي
After 9/11,
بعد 9\11
either you were with us or against us.
اما ان تكون معنا او ضدنا.
It was black or white.
كان الأمر إمّا اسود او ابيض.
And groups are very often
وكانت الجماعات في معظم الوقت
immediately label terrorists.
توصف بكونها ارهابية.
And who would talk to terrorists?
ومن يرغب في الحديث مع ارهابيين؟
The West, as I would see it,
الغرب كما اراه,
comes out of that decade weakened,
عاد من ذلك العقد اضعف حالا
because we didn't understand the group.
لأننا لم نعي مفهوم الجماعة
So we've spent more time
لذلك استغرقنا وقت اكثر
on focusing on why we should not talk to others
في التركيز على لماذا يجب ان لا نتحدث مع الاخرين
than finding out how we talk to others.
اكثر من البحث عن كيف نتحدث معهم
Now I'm not naive.
انا لست ساذجا.
You cannot talk to everybody all the time.
لا يمكنك الحديث مع الجميع طوال الوقت.
And there are times you should walk.
وهناك لحظات يجب ان تتحرك
And sometimes military intervention is necessary.
وبعض الاوقات يكون التدخل العسكري ضروريا
I happen to believe that Libya was necessary
حدث وان امنت ان التدخل العسكري في ليبيا كان ضروريا
and that military intervention in Afghanistan was also necessary.
والتدخل العسكري في افغانستان كان ايضا ضروريا
And my country relies on its security
ودولتنا تعتمد على امنها
through military alliance, that's clear.
من خلال التحالفات العسكرية ,هذا واضح
But still we have a large deficit
لكن مازال لدينا عجز
in dealing with and understanding modern conflict.
في التعامل وفهم الصراعات الحديثة
Let us turn to Afghanistan.
دعونا نتوجه الى افغانستان
10 years after that military intervention,
عشر سنوات بعد التدخل العسكري
that country is far from secure.
الدولة بعيدة كل البعد عن الامن
The situation, to be honest, is very serious.
الوضع, وبصراحة, خطير جدا.
Now again, the military is necessary,
مرة اخرى التدخل العسكري ضروري
but the military is no problem-solver.
لكن التدخل العسكري لا يحل المشاكل
When I first came to Afghanistan in 2005 as a foreign minister,
عندما زرت افغانستان اول مرة في 2005 كوزير للخارجية
I met the commander of ISAF,
قابلت قائد ايساف (قوة المساعدة الامنية الدولية),
the international troops.
القوات الدولية.
And he told me that, "This can be won militarily, minister.
اخبرني انه,"يمكن كسب هذه المعرك,سيادة الوزير.
We just have to persevere."
نحتاج الى المثابرة."
Now four COM ISAF's later,
الان وبعد اربعة قادة لايساف ,
we hear a different message:
نسمع رسالة مختلفة
"This cannot be won militarily.
"لايمكن كسب ذلك عسكريا.
We need military presence,
نحتاج وجود عسكري,
but we need to move to politics.
لكن نحتاج الى التوجه الى السياسة.
We can only solve this through a political solution.
يمكننا حل ذلك من خلال حل سياسي
And it is not us who will solve it;
ولسنا نحن من سيقوم بحلها,
Afghans have to solve it."
الافغان يجب ان يحلوها"
But then they need a different political process
لكنهم حينها يحتاجون عملية سياسية مختلفة
than the one they were given in 2001, 2002.
عما تم تقديمه في 2001 ,2002.
They need an inclusive process
يحتاجون لعملية شاملة
where the real fabric of this very complicated society
بحيث ان النسيج الحقيقي لهذا المجتمع المعقد
can deal with their issues.
يتمكن من معالجة قضاياهم
Everybody seems to agree with that.
الجميع يبدو موافقا على ذلك
It was very controversial to say three, four, five years ago.
كان مثار الجدل قول ذلك قبل اربعة او خمسة سنوات
Now everybody agrees.
الان الجميع موافق
But now, as we prepare to talk,
لكن الان ونحن نتجهز للحديث,
we understand how little we know.
نفهم مدى قلة ما نعرفه
Because we didn't talk.
لأننا لم نتحدث
We didn't grasp what was going on.
لم نفهم مالذي كان يحدث
The International Committee of the Red Cross, the ICRC,
اللجنة الدولية للصليب الاحمر , اي سي ار سي
is talking to everyone,
تتحدث للجميع
and it is doing so because it is neutral.
وتفعل ذلك لانها محايدة
And that's one reason why
وهذا احد الاسباب الذي يفسر لماذا
that organization probably
تلك المنظمة تقريبا
is the best informed key player
افضل لاعب رئيسي
to understand modern conflict --
قادر على فهم الصراع الحديث
because they talk.
لانهم يتحدثون
My point is that you don't have to be neutral to talk.
نقطتي هي انه لا يجب عليك ان تكون محايدا للتحدث
And you don't have to agree
ولا يجب عليك الموافقة
when you sit down with the other side.
عندما تجلس مع الجانب الاخر
And you can always walk.
ويمكنك دائما الانصراف
But if you don't talk,
لكن اذا لم تتحدث
you can't engage the other side.
لا يمكنك التواصل مع الطرف الاخر
And the other side which you're going to engage
والجانب الاخر الذي سوف تتواصل معه
is the one with whom you profoundly disagree.
هو الجانب الذي لديك خلاف عميق معه
Prime Minister Rabin said when he engaged the Oslo process,
رئيس وزراء اسرائيل رابين قال عندما انخرط في عملية اوسلو
"You don't make peace with your friends,
"انت لا تعمل سلام مع اصدقاءك,
you make peace with your enemies."
انت تعمل سلام مع اعداءك"
It's hard, but it is necessary.
ذلك صعب لكنه ضروري
Let me go one step further.
دعوني انتقل خطوة للامام
This is Tahrir Square.
هذا هو ميدان التحرير
There's a revolution going on.
الثورة مستمرة
The Arab Spring is heading into fall
الربيع العربي يتحول الى خريف
and is moving into winter.
وفي اتجاهه الى الشتاء.
It will last for a long, long time.
سوف يبقى لوقت طويل جدا جدا
And who knows what it will be called in the end.
ولا احد يعرف مالذي سوف يسموه في النهاية
That's not the point.
هذه ليست المسألة.
The point is that we are probably seeing,
المسألة هي اننا نشاهد
for the first time in the history of the Arab world,
لاول مرة في تاريخ العالم العربي
a revolution bottom-up --
ثورة من القاعدة الى الاعلى
people's revolution.
ثورة شعبية
Social groups are taking to the streets.
مجموعات اجتماعية تقود الشوارع
And we find out in the West
واكتشفنا في الغرب
that we know very little about what's happening.
اننا نعرف القليل عن الذي يحدث
Because we never talk to the people in these countries.
لاننا لم نتحدث مطلقا مع الناس في تلك الدول
Most governments followed
معظم الحكومات تتبع
the dictate of the authoritarian leaders
الاملاءت الدكتاتورية للحكام
to stay away from these different groups,
للابتعاد عن تلك المجموعات
because they were terrorists.
لانهم كانوا ارهابيين
So now that they are emerging in the street
الان وهم يسيطرون على الشارع
and we salute the democratic revolution,
ونشاهد ثورة ديموقراطية
we find out how little we know.
اكتشفنا كم هو قليل ما نعرفه
Right now, the discussion goes,
حاليا يتجه النقاش الى
"Should we talk to the Muslim Brotherhood?
"هل نتحدث مع الاخوان المسلمين؟
Should we talk to Hamas?
هل نتحدث مع حماس؟
If we talk to them, we may legitimize them."
اذا تحدثنا معهم ربما اعطيناهم شرعية:
I think that is wrong.
اعتقد ان ذلك خطأ
If you talk in the right way, you make it very clear
اذا تحدثت بالطريقة الصحيحة سوف توضح الامور
that talking is not agreeing.
ان الحديث لا يعني الموافقة
And how can we tell the Muslim Brotherhood,
وكيف يمكننا اخبار الاخوان المسلمين,
as we should,
كما يجب علينا
that they must respect minority rights,
ان عليهم ان يحترموا حقوق الاقلية
if we don't accept majority rights?
اذا لم نتقبل حقوق الاغلبية؟
Because they may turn out to be a majority.
لانه ربما يتضح انهم الاغلبية
How can we escape [having] a double-standard,
كيف يمكننا الافلات ونحن نستخدم معايير مزدوجة
if we at the same time preach democracy
اذا كنا في الوقت الذي نقدم فيه مواعظ عن الديموقراطية
and at the same time
وفي نفس الوقت
don't want to deal with the groups that are representative?
لا نريد التعامل مع المجموعات الممثلة للشارع
How will we ever be interlocutors?
كيف يمكن ان نكون محاورين؟
Now my diplomats are instructed
الان لدي موظفيّ الدوبلماسيين تعليمات
to talk to all these groups.
بأن يتحدثوا مع تلك المجموعات
But talking can be done in different ways.
لكن الحديث يمكن ان يكون بطرق مختلفة
We make a distinction between talking from a diplomatic level
يمكننا التفريق بين الحديث على المستوى الدبلوماسي,
and talking at the political level.
والحديث من المستوى السياسي
Now talking can be accompanied with aid or not with aid.
الان الحديث يمكن ان يترافق مع معونة او بدون معونة
Talking can be accompanied with inclusion or not inclusion.
الحديث يمكن ان يترافق مع ضمانات او بدون ضمانات
There's a big array
هناك مجموعة كبيرة
of the ways of dealing with this.
من الطرق للتعامل مع هذا
So if we refuse
فاذا رفضنا
to talk to these new groups
الحديث الى تلك الجماعات الجديدة
that are going to be dominating the news in years to come,
والتي سوف تكون مهيمنه على الاخبار لسنين قادمة
we will further radicalization,
سندعم التطرف
I believe.
اعتقد ذلك
We will make the road from violent activities into politics
سوف نجعل الطريق من الانشطة العنيفة الى السياسة
harder to travel.
ذات المسالك الوعر
And if we cannot demonstrate to these groups
ولن يمكننا الشرح لتلك الجماعات
that if you move towards democracy,
انه اذا اجهتم نحو الديمو قراطية
if you move towards taking part
واذا اتجهتم نحو اعتماد
in civilized and normal standards among states,
مبادئ مدنية تجاه الدول
there are some rewards on the other side.
سوف يكون هناك مكافاءت في المقابل
The paradox here
المفارقة هنا
is that the last decade probably was a lost decade
ان العقد الماضي كان عقدا ضائعا تقريبا
for making progress on this.
لعمل تقدم في هذا الاتجاه
And the paradox is that the decade before the last decade was so promising --
ان العقد السابق للعقد المنصرم كان واعدا
and for one reason primarily.
ولاكثر من سبب
And the reason is what happened in South Africa:
والسبب ان ما حدث في جنوب افريقيا
Nelson Mandela.
نيلسون مانديلا
When Mandela came out of prison
عندما خرج مانديلا من السجن
after 27 years of captivity,
بعد 27 عاما من الاسر
if he had told his people,
لو كان اخبر اتباعه
"It's time to take up the arms,
"انه حان وقت رفع السواعد,
it's time to fight,"
حان وقت القتال"
he would have been followed.
سوف يجد من يتبعه
And I think the international community
واعتقد ان المجتمع الدولي
would have said, "Fair enough.
سوف يقول " هذا عادل بما فيه الكفاية
It's their right to fight."
هذا حقهم في القتال"
Now as you know, Mandela didn't do that.
والان كما تعلمون مانديلا لم يفعل ذلك
In his memoirs, "Long Road to Freedom,"
في مذكراته," الطريق الطويل للحرية"
he wrote that he survived
كتب ان سبب نجاته
during those years of captivity
خلال تلك السنين من الاسر
because he always decided to look upon his oppressor
انه قرر ان ينظر دائما الى مضطهده
as also being a human being,
على انه انسان
So he engaged a political process of dialogue,
لذلك هو انخرط في عملية سياسية من الحوار
not as a strategy of the weak,
ليس باستراتيجية الضعف
but as a strategy of the strong.
ولكن باستراتيجية القوة
And he engaged talking profoundly
وانخرط في حوار عميق
by settling some of the most tricky issues
عن طريق حل بعض اكثر القضايا صعوبة
through a truth and reconciliation process
من خلال عملية الحقيقة و المصالحة
where people came and talked.
حيث اتى الناس وتحدثوا
Now South African friends will know
الان الأصدقاء من جنوب افريقيا سوف يعرفون
that was very painful.
ان ذلك كان مؤلم جدا
So what can we learn from all of this?
مالذي يمكننا تعلمه من هذا
Dialogue is not easy --
الحوار ليس سهلا --
not between individuals, not between groups, not between governments --
ليس بين الافراد, و لا بين الجماعات, و لا بين الحكومات--
but it is very necessary.
لكنه ضروري جدا.
If we're going to deal with political conflict-solving of conflicts,
اذا كنا عازمين على التعامل مع حل الصراعات سياسيا
if we're going to understand these new groups
ا اذا كنا نريد فهم تلك الجماعات الجديدة
which are coming from bottom-up,
الذين ياتون من الاسفل الى الاعلى
supported by technology, which is available to all,
مدعومة بالتكنلوجيا المتوفرة.
we diplomats cannot be sitting back in the banquets
نحن الدبلوماسيون , لا يمكننا الجلوس في الولائم
believing that we are doing interstate relations.
معتقدين اننا نعمل علاقات بين الدول.
We have to connect
يجب ان نتواصل
with these profound changes.
مع تلك التغييرات العميقة
And what is dialogue really about?
ومالذي يجب ان يكون عليه الحوار؟
When I enter into dialogue,
عندما ادخل في حوار,
I really hope that the other side
اكون على امل ان الجانب الاخر
would pick up my points of view,
سوف يلتقط وجهة نظري,
that I would impress upon them
التي سوف اؤثر بها عليه
my opinions and my values.
افكاري وقيمي
I cannot do that
لا استطيع عمل ذلك.
unless I send the signals that I will be open
الا اذا ارسلت اشارات انني منفتح
to listen to the other side's signals.
على الاستماع الى اشارات الجانب الاخر
We need a lot more training on how to do that
نحتاج الى الكثير من التدريب على كيفية عمل ذلك
and a lot more practice
والكثير من الممارسة
on how that can take problem-solving forward.
على كيف يمكن لذلك دعم حل المشكلة
We know from our personal experiences
نعلم من خلال خبراتنا الشخصية
that it's easy sometimes
انه من السهل احيانا
just to walk,
ان تنصرف,
and sometimes you may need to fight.
واحيانا تحتاج للقتال
And I wouldn't say that is the wrong thing in all circumstances.
ولن اقول ان ذلك خطأ في جميع الظروف
Sometimes you have to.
بعض الاحيان يجب ان تفعل ذلك
But that strategy seldom takes you very far.
لكن تلك الاستراتيجية من النادر أن تؤتي ثمارها
The alternative is a strategy
البديل هو استراتيجية
of engagement and principled dialogue.
الانخراط في حوار مؤسس
And I believe we need to strengthen this approach
واعتقد اننا نحتاج الى تقوية هذا النهج
in modern diplomacy,
في الدبلوماسية الحديثة,
not only between states,
ليس بين الدول فقط
but also within states.
لكن ايضا داخل الدول
We are seeing some new signs.
نرى بعض المؤشرات
We could never have done
لم نستطع عمل
the convention against anti-personnel landmines
اتفاقية ضد الالغام المضادة للافراد
and the convention that is banning cluster munitions
والاتفاقات التي تحضر الذخيرة الحية
unless we had done diplomacy differently,
الا اذا مارسنا الدبلوماسية بطريقة مختلفة
by engaging with civil society.
بالاندماج مع المجتمع المدني
All of a sudden,
بمحض الصدفة
NGOs were not only standing in the streets, crying their slogans,
المنظمات غير الحكومية كانت تقف في الشوارع ينادون بشعارتهم فقط
but they were taking [them] into the negotiations,
لكن بأخذهم في حوارات
partly because they represented the victims of these weapons.
جزئيا لانهم يمثلون ضحايا تلك الاسلحة
And they brought their knowledge.
ويجلبون معرفتهم
And there was an interaction
وهناك تفاعل
between diplomacy and the power coming bottom-up.
بين الدبلوماسية وقوة القدوم من القاعدة
This is perhaps a first element
هذا ربما العنصر الاساسي
of a change.
للتغيير
In the future, I believe,
في المستقبل اعتقد
we should draw examples from these different illustrations,
يجب علينا ان نرسم امثلة من هذه الشواهد المختلفة
not to have diplomacy
ليس للحصول على دبلوماسية
which is disconnected from people and civil society.
معزولة عن الناس والمجتمع المدني
And we have to go also
وعلينا المضي ايضا
beyond traditional diplomacy
الى ما وراء الدبلوماسية التقليدية
to the survival issue of our times,
الى القضية المصيرية في وقتنا
climate change.
التغير المناخي
How are we going to solve climate change through negotiations,
كيف يمكننا حل التغير المناخي من خلال الحوارات
unless we are able to make civil society and people,
الا اذا كنا قادرين على جعل الناس والمجتمع
not part of the problem, but part of the solution?
ليسو جزءا من المشكلة ولكن جزءا من الحل؟
It is going to demand an inclusive process of diplomacy
سوف يتطلب ذلك عملية دبلوماسية
very different from the one we are practicing today
مختلفة تماما عن التي نمارسها اليوم
as we are heading to new rounds of difficult climate negotiations,
ونحن نعبر جولات صعبة من المفاوضات,
but when we move toward something
ولكن عندما ننتقل الى شي
which has to be much more
الى شيء اكبر
along a broad mobilization.
يتخطى الحدود
It's crucial to understand, I believe,
اعتقد انه شيء يجب فهمه
because of technology and because of globalization,
بسبب التقنية وبسبب العولمة
societies from bottom-up.
المجتمعات من القاع الى الاعلى
We as diplomats
نحن كدبلوماسيين
need to know the social capital
نحتاج ان نعرف رأس المال المجتمعي
of communities.
للمجموعات
What is it that makes people trust each other,
مالذي يجعل الناس يثقون ببعضهم البعض
not only between states,
ليس بين الدول فقط
but also within states?
ولكن داخل الدول ايضا؟
What is the legitimacy of diplomacy,
ماهي شرعية الدبلوماسية
of the the solution we devise as diplomats
للحلول التي نبتكرها كدبلوماسيين
if they cannot be reflected and understood
اذا كان لا يمكن انعكاسها وفهمها
by also these broader forces of societies
من قبل تلك القوى الاوسع من المجتمعات
that we now very loosely call groups?
و التي نسميها مجازا الجماعات؟
The good thing is that we are not powerless.
الشيء الجيد اننا لسنا بدون طاقة
We have never had
لم نحصل ابدا
as many means of communication,
على قدر من اوجه التواصل
means of being connected, means of reaching out,
اوجه الاتصال واوجه التفاعل,
means of including.
اوجه الشمول
The diplomatic toolbox
ادوات الدبلوماسية
is actually full of different tools we can use
مليئة فعليا بادوات مختلفة يمكن ان نستخدمها
to strengthen our communication.
لتقوية تواصلنا
But the problem is that we are coming out of a decade
لكن المشكلة اننا قادمون من عقد من الزمان
where we had a fear of touching it.
كان لدينا تخوف من لمسها
Now, I hope, in the coming years,
الان اطمح انه في السنين القادمة
that we are able to demonstrate through some concrete examples
اننا سوف نكون قادرين على شرح بعض الامثلة الصلبة
that fear is receding
التي تقلص الخوف
and that we can take courage
والتي نكتسب منها الشجاعة
from that alliance
من ذلك التحالف
with civil society
مع المجتمع المدني
in different countries
في دول مختلفة
to support their problem-solving,
لدعم حل مشاكلهم
among the Afghans,
الافغان
inside the Palestinian population,
داخل الفلسطينيين
between the peoples of Palestine and Israel.
بين شعب فلسطين و اسرائيل
And as we try to understand this broad movement
ونحن نحاول فهم هذا التحرك الواسع
across the Arab world,
في العالم العربي
we are not powerless.
نحن لسنا عاجزين
We need to improve the necessary skills,
نحتاج الى تطوير المهارات الضرورية
and we need the courage to use them.
ونحتاج الى الشجاعة في استخدامها
In my country,
في بلدي
I have seen how the council of Islamist groups
رايت كيف ان مجلس الجماعات الاسلامية
and Christian groups
والجماعات المسيحية
came together, not as a government initiative,
اجتمعوا معا , ليس بمبادرة من الحكومة
but they came together on their own initiative
ولكنهم اجتمعوا بمبادرة منهم
to establish contact and dialogue
لتأسيس حوار و تواصل
in times where things were pretty low-key tension.
في اوقات كانت الامور منخفضة التوتر
And when tension increased,
وعندما يزداد التوتر,
they already had that dialogue,
يكونو قد بدأوا ذلك الحوار
and that was a strength to deal with different issues.
وذلك مصدر قوة للتعامل مع القضايا المختلفة
Our modern Western societies
مجتمعاتنا الغربية الحديثة
are more complex than before,
معقدة اكثر من السابق
in this time of migration.
في هذا الوقت من الهجرة
How are we going to settle and build a bigger "We"
كيف سوف نقوم بحل وبناء "نحن" كبيره
to deal with our issues
للتعامل مع قضايانا
if we don't improve our skills of communication?
اذا لم نطور مهاراتنا في التواصل؟
So there are many reasons,
اذا هناك اسباب عديده,
and for all of these reasons,
ولكل تلك الاسباب,
this is time and this is why we must talk.
هذا هو الوقت والسبب لكي نتحدث
Thank you for your attention.
شكرا لانصاتكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)